Welcome back to making chatbots.
챗봇 만들기입니다 안녕하세요
Let's keep going.
계속하죠
So for the next part we're going to beef up the system message to something a bit more interesting.
다음 부분에서는 시스템 메시지를 좀 더 흥미롭게 비트로 업그레이드할 거예요
System message.
시스템 메시지예요
You're a helpful assistant in a clothes store.
옷 가게의 도우미로 일하죠
You should try to gently encourage the customer to try items on sale.
세일 중인 제품을 입어 보라고 부드럽게 격려해 주세요
Hats off 60% off.
60% 할인이라니 대단해요
Most other items are 50% off.
다른 건 50% 할인해요
For example, if the customer says I'm looking to buy a hat, you could reply, wonderful!
예를 들어 손님이 모자를 사러 왔다고 하면 아주 좋다고 대답하면 돼요
We have lots of hats, including several part of our sales event.
판매 행사에 쓸 모자가 아주 많아요
Encourage the customer to buy hats if they're unsure what to get.
Get it. 어떤 걸 사야 할지 모를 땐 모자를 사라고 권장하세요
So what you're seeing here is a few things going on in this system prompt.
시스템 프롬프트에서 몇 가지 일이 일어나고 있어요
We've got some facts that are being provided about the sales, the hats and other items.
판매와 모자, 기타 물품에 대한 정보를 입수했어요
Um, you've got an example, an example of if the customer says this, you could say that.
예를 들어보죠 고객이 이걸 말하면 저걸 말하면 돼요
And that example both is a way to establish tone and style.
그 두 가지 예는 분위기와 스타일을 설정하는 방법이죠
Um, and it's also a way to introduce more facts about hats, uh, into the conversation.
모자에 관한 더 많은 사실을 대화에 소개하는 방법이기도 하죠
So this is all example of one shot prompting.
이게 다 원샷 프롬프트 예죠
And you could argue Multi-shot prompting.
멀티샷 프롬핑을 논할 수도 있어요
So we're giving it a few different sort of nuances of how to reply.
어떻게 응답할지 미묘한 차이를 주고 있어요
Um, and building that into the system message.
그걸 시스템 메시지로 구축하는 거죠
There are other ways of doing it that we'll talk about, or at least at least another way of doing it.
다른 방법도 있어요 나중에 얘기하거나 적어도 다른 방법이요
But this is one very effective way.
하지만 이건 아주 효과적인 방법이에요
So we we add in that system message, and we're now going to have a chat with the with with the chat
이 시스템 메시지를 추가하면 채팅 봇과 채팅을 할 수 있어요
So again we write our method of our generator chat um which takes a message and history because that's
그래서 다시 발전기 채팅 방식을 작성해요 메시지와 역사가 필요하죠 그라디오가 그걸로 연락하고
what Gradio wants to call us with.
싶어 하거든요
Um, and we first convert that into the format that OpenAI expects, um, by building the usual list
먼저 오픈AI가 기대하는 포맷으로 변환합니다 여러분이 익숙한 목록을 작성함으로써요
I should also mention, I don't know if I mentioned this last time, that at the end here we have to
또 하나 언급할 것은 지난 시간에 말했는지 모르겠는데 여기 마지막에
add in, of course, into that list the latest message that the user is sending that gets added to the
우린 물론 리스트에 추가해야 합니다 사용자가 보내는 가장 최근 메시지를 역할 사용자 콘텐츠로 하단에
bottom as role user content.
추가해야 하죠
And that message.
그 메시지도요
Then of course, we make a call that at this point, you have ingrained in your deepest memory the create
물론 이때쯤이면 가장 깊은 메모리에 새겨진 create 호출을 사용하고 스트리밍
call and we have stream is true and we stream back results.
이즈 true로 결과를 스트리밍하죠
So here we go.
자, 시작하죠
We'll bring that up.
그 얘기도 하죠
We'll bring it up in a separate window again.
다른 창에서 다시 보여드릴게요
Why not.
안 될 거 없죠
And let's talk to our shopping assistant.
쇼핑 보조와 얘기해 보죠
Hi there.
안녕하세요
Welcome to our store.
어서 오세요
How can I assist you today?
무엇을 도와드릴까요?
Are you looking for anything specific?
특별히 찾는 게 있나요?
Say, uh, I'd like to buy some shoes.
신발을 좀 사고 싶은데요
Great.
좋아요
We have a lovely selection.
예쁜 게 많아요
While you're browsing, I want to mention we have a fantastic sale going on.
여러분이 보시는 동안 세일을 말씀드릴게요
Most items are 50% off.
대부분 50% 할인해요
If you're open to it, we have some stylish hats that are 60% off.
괜찮으시면 60% 할인된 멋진 모자가 있어요
They might be the perfect complement to your new shoes.
새 신발과 잘 어울릴 거예요
Would you like to take a look at both?
둘 다 보시겠어요?
So I want to point out that that it's obviously figured out.
그래서 제가 말씀드리고 싶은 건 확실히 해결됐다는 거예요
It's got the knowledge that we supplied to it in the system prompt.
시스템 프롬프트에 제공한 지식이 있어요
But you hopefully will also notice that the sort of enthusiastic, effusive style that I used in that
하지만 제가 시스템 프롬프트에 사용한 열정적이고 활발한
system prompt has rubbed off in a way that it's communicating in this kind of, uh, very, uh, amiable
스타일이 이런 식으로 소통하는 방식으로 전염됐다는 걸 눈치채셨길 바라요
Um, and that's a big part of this kind of one shot or multi-shot prompting when you set the tone,
이런 원샷 또는 멀티샷 프롬핑에서 중요한 부분이죠 분위기를 설정할 때
give examples of how it should reply.
어떻게 응답해야 할지 예제를 제시하세요
Uh, so let's keep going.
계속 진행하죠
Let's take that system message and and add in.
시스템 메시지를 추가하죠
If the customer asks for shoes, you could respond that shoes are not on sale.
손님이 신발을 찾으시면 세일 중인 신발이 아니라고 대답하세요
Let's say should respond.
대응해야 한다고 해두죠
Should respond that shoes are not on sale today.
신발은 오늘 세일 안 한다고 대답하세요
But remind the customer to look at hats.
손님들께 모자를 보여주세요
So let's try this again.
다시 해 보죠
Let's see how this does.
어떻게 되나 보죠
Uh, it's got another fact to add.
하나 더 있어요
Uh, you could argue that that's.
그렇게 볼 수도 있겠네요
Yeah, that's like another, uh, multi-shot prompt.
네, 그것도 멀티샷 프롬프트죠
Let's say.
이렇게 하죠
Hi there.
안녕하세요
Are you looking.
보고 있어요?
I'd like to buy some shoes.
신발을 좀 사려고요
That sounds great.
좋아요
I should mention shoes aren't on sale today.
오늘 신발 세일 안 해요
But while you're here, have you thought about checking out our hats?
여기 오신 김에 우리 모자도 구경해 보실래요?
You've got to feel sorry for this poor customer who's going to get repeatedly pitched hats.
Get it's go 계속 얻어맞을 불쌍한 손님을 불쌍히 여겨 주세요
Um, so you can see again how it's established, um, that shoes aren't on sale, but that hats very
그래서 어떻게 확립됐는지 다시 볼 수 있죠 신발은 세일하지 않지만 모자는 세일한다는
much are.
거요
And that is an example, then, of Multi-shot prompting, uh, in that we're giving it more examples
그게 멀티샷 프롬프트 예입니다 배울 수 있는 예시를 더 제공하는
to learn from.
거죠
Um, so another thing that we can do that is interesting, um, is that whenever you've seen these constructions
우리가 할 수 있는 또 다른 흥미로운 것은 지금까지 이런 건축을 보실 때마다 항상 시스템 메시지로
so far, you've always seen us beginning with the system message.
시작하는 걸 보셨을 거예요
The system messages come at the top.
시스템 메시지는 상단에 있어요
But in fact, with the OpenAI call, there's you're not constrained to have the system message at the
하지만 OpenAI 호출에서는 상단에 시스템 메시지가 있어야 한다는 제약이 없어요
top.
시스템 메시지는 가면서 추가하세요
Um, and so for example, one of the things we can do, um, uh, and let me apologize for some very
예를 들어 우리가 할 수 있는 것 중 하나는 아주 해커 같은 코드에 대해 사과드립니다 권장하진 않지만
hacky code here that I will not recommend, but it's here to show the example.
예제를 보여주기 위해 여기 나와있어요
It's not the way that you should do it in practice, but what we could do is when we're building this
실제론 그렇게 하면 안 되지만 채팅 생성기를 만들 때 할 수 있는
chat generator, we could put in here if this current message that the user is sending us contains the
건 여기에 넣는 거죠 사용자가 보내는 현재 메시지가 워드 벨트를 포함한다면요
And you can see in a rather unawesome way, I've just looked for the string belt.
다소 민망한 방법이지만 문자열 벨트를 찾아봤어요
Of course, I should be testing whether it's the full word, and I should be thinking about uppercase,
물론 완전한 단어인지 테스트해야 하고 대문자, 소문자 등을
lowercase and so on.
생각해야 하죠
I'm not doing any of that, which is very naughty of me, but it shows the point.
전 그런 거 안 해요 못된 짓이지만 요점은 알겠죠
So if belt is in the word message, it's going to add into this set of messages.
벨트가 메시지 안에 있으면 이 메시지 모음에 추가될 거예요
Another system message saying for added context, the store does not sell belts, but be sure to point
또 다른 시스템 메시지는 추가 컨텍스트를 위해 마트는 벨트를 팔지 않습니다 하지만
out items on sale so that will be then added in to the prompt if the user asks for a belt.
세일 중인 아이템을 꼭 지적하세요 사용자가 벨트를 요청하면 프롬프트에 추가될 거예요
So let's give that a try and bring this up here.
한 번 해보죠 이걸 여기로 불러와요
Hi there.
안녕하세요
Welcome to the store.
어서 오세요
I can assist you.
제가 도와드릴게요
I'd like to buy a belt.
벨트 하나 사려고요
I'm sorry.
미안해요
We don't carry belts.
벨트는 없어요
However, we have fantastic items, including hats.
하지만 모자도 있고 멋진 아이템도 있어요
60% off.
60% 할인요
So there you go.
자, 됐어요
There you go.
여기요
It's, um.
네
Uh, definitely pays attention.
확실히 주의를 기울이죠
You can see that when the system message is added in as another row in this, uh, in this list of messages,
시스템 메시지가 이 메시지 목록의 다른 행으로 추가되면 주의를
it pays attention to it.
기울이죠
And that gives us the opportunity to add context into the conversation.
대화에 맥락을 추가할 기회를 주는 거죠
And this is a, uh, whilst it is, of course, uh, very kludgy code to be detecting a word, a substring
단어나 비트링을 감지하는 건 매우 복잡한 코드지만 좀 더 튼튼하게
like that, you can imagine that you could beef this up to be a bit more robust.
만들 수도 있어요
You could properly you could have a little dictionary which looks for particular words.
특정 단어를 찾는 작은 사전도 하나 있어야 해요
And when it finds them, it could use them to then enrich the the context in the right way.
그걸 찾으면 적절한 방식으로 문맥을 풍부하게 하는 거죠
So it gives you a little, a little ability to be looking things up and adding them into the context.
따라서 여러분이 뭔가를 찾아 컨텍스트에 추가할 수 있는 능력을 주죠
Now, you may be familiar with with some things about Rag, and you may be aware that that is a lot
랙에 대해 좀 아실지도 모르겠네요 랙이 의미하는 바가 아주 크다는 것도
of what rag is about.
알 거예요
Rag is about finding extra information that's relevant to the prompt, and adding it in to the context
Rag는 프롬프트와 관련된 추가 정보를 찾아 LM으로 전송되는 메시지의 컨텍스트에
of the message that gets sent to the LM.
추가하는 거죠
Now, of course, Rag does that in a much more sophisticated and intelligent way than this hokey piece
물론 래그는 훨씬 더 정교하고 똑똑한 방법으로 그걸 하죠 여기 이 진부한 코드보다는요
But you can think of this as a as a light, a baby version of rag, and as an exercise for you.
하지만 이걸 조명이나 아기용 랙이라고 생각해도 돼요 운동으로 생각하세요
You can certainly beef this up a bit, and at the very least, use regex to make it look for a particular
비트를 좀 더 보강할 수도 있어요 적어도 레벡스를 써서 특정 단어를 찾아볼 수
word.
있죠
Maybe have a little dictionary that has the the words, the different items in the store together with
작은 사전을 하나 준비하세요 스토어에 있는 다양한 아이템의 가격을 함께
their price so that you could add that in as a system message to give it more context.
적어서 시스템 메시지로 추가하는 거죠 컨텍스트를 더 주려고요
You could try that out and see that you could build a chatbot that actually knows about the prices of
시험해 보고 챗봇을 만들 수 있다는 걸 알 수 있어요 스토어에 있는 상품의 가격을
the goods in its store, and that would be pretty cool.
아는 챗봇요 그럼 멋질 거예요
So that wraps up this particular experiment.
이번 실험은 여기까지예요
I do just want to mention, I alluded earlier to the fact that there are other ways of doing Multi-shot
아까 언급하고 싶은 게 있었는데 멀티샷 프롬프트를 시스템 프롬프트에
prompting other than shoving it in the system prompt, and the other way is that you can have a user
밀어 넣는 것 말고 다른 방법도 있어요 다른 방법은 사용자 비서가 있는 거죠 사용자 비서가
assistant, user assistant set of messages that hasn't actually happened.
메시지 세트를 갖는 건데 실제로 일어나지 않았어요
You can have a fictitious exchange between the user and the assistant that you include in the conversation
사용자와 비서 사이의 가상의 교환을 가질 수 있습니다 현재 대화
before the current conversation, and use that as a way to prime the LM with similar conversations,
전에 포함된 대화에요 그걸 LM을 프라임하는 방법으로 사용할 수 있습니다
so that it gets a sense of how it's responded to other questions.
다른 질문에 어떻게 반응했는지 감을 잡을 수 있도록요
You can use that again, both to train it on style and also to supply extra facts.
다시 한번 써먹으세요 스타일 훈련도 하고 추가 정보도 제공하고요
So there could have been an earlier interaction when there had been a question about a belt, and the
그 전에 벨트에 관한 질문이 들어왔을 때 비서가 이미 매장에 벨트가
assistant had already replied that there are no belts in the store, and it would have learnt from that.
없다고 답했을 수도 있어요 그럼 거기서 배웠겠죠
So either technique, they have pros and cons, whether you supply it in system prompts or whether you
기술에는 장단점이 있습니다 시스템 프롬프트에서 제공하든
give example user assistant interactions for it to have as part of the input context for it to to be
사용자 보조 상호 작용을 제공하든 입력 컨텍스트의 일부로 받아들일 수 있도록요
Um, and my ask to you is to try them both out.
둘 다 시험해 보고 싶어요
So update this so that it uses user assistant interactions instead of a system prompt and see how that
이걸 업데이트해 사용자 비서 상호 작용을 사용하도록 하세요 시스템 프롬프트 대신에요 어떻게 되는지
works.
보시죠
See if you think you get a better or a worse clothes store assistant.
Get it get it get it get it get it get it get it a good-tures good.
And then also make this change to make this a whole lot more robust, have a dictionary of different
그리고 이걸 훨씬 더 견고하게 만들 이 변화도 가하세요 스토어에 있는
items in the store, look up their prices or their sale amounts, and then add that as context into
다양한 아이템에 대한 사전을 만들고 가격이나 판매 금액을 찾아보세요 그런 다음
the conversation so that the assistant responds with some expertise and have fun doing it, and I will
그걸 대화에 추가해 비서가 전문 지식으로 답변할 수 있도록요 재미있게 하세요 오늘을 마무리할
see you for the next video to wrap up this day.
다음 비디오에서 뵙죠